<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<article dtd="RSCART3.8" type="COM" xmlns="http://www.rsc.org/schema/rscart38" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.rsc.org/schema/rscart38 http://www.rsc.org/schema/rscart38/rscart38.xsd" xmlns:tmp="http://www.rsc.org/editing" tmp:status="aaprep">
<art-admin>
<ms-id>c7cc05669a</ms-id>
<doi>10.1039/c7cc05669a</doi>
<received>
<date><year>2017</year><month>August</month><day>25</day></date>
</received>
<date role="accepted"><year>2017</year><month>October</month><day>9</day></date>
</art-admin>


<published type="web"><journalref><link>CC</link></journalref><volumeref><link>Unassigned</link></volumeref><issueref><link>Advance Articles</link></issueref><pubfront><fpage></fpage><lpage></lpage><no-of-pages></no-of-pages><date><year>2017</year><month>October</month><day>16</day></date></pubfront></published><published type="print"><journalref><link>CC</link></journalref><volumeref><link></link></volumeref><issueref><link></link></issueref><pubfront><fpage></fpage><lpage></lpage><no-of-pages></no-of-pages><date><year>Unassigned</year><month>Unassigned</month><day>Unassigned</day></date></pubfront></published><published type="subsyear"><journalref><link>CC</link></journalref><volumeref><link></link></volumeref><issueref><link></link></issueref><pubfront><fpage></fpage><lpage></lpage><no-of-pages></no-of-pages><date><year>2017</year><month>Unassigned</month><day>Unassigned</day></date></pubfront></published><art-links>
<suppinf><link>INFO</link></suppinf>
<fundgrp>
<funder>
<funder-name>Bundesministerium für Wirtschaft und Energie</funder-name>
<funder-identifier>10.13039/501100006360</funder-identifier>
<award-number>03ESP106D</award-number>
</funder>
</fundgrp>
</art-links>
<art-front>
<titlegrp>
<title>The active site for the water oxidising anodic iridium oxide probed through <it>in situ</it> Raman spectroscopy<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref><footnote id="fn1">Electronic supplementary information (ESI) available: Experimental details, cyclic voltammograms, Raman spectra in various electrochemical media and computational details. See DOI: <url>10.1039/c7cc05669a</url></footnote></title>
</titlegrp>
<authgrp>
<author aff="affa"><person orcid="0000-0002-4965-8458"><persname><fname>Zoran</fname><surname>Pavlovic</surname></persname></person></author>
<author aff="affa" role="corres"><person orcid="0000-0002-3758-3751"><persname><fname>Chinmoy</fname><surname>Ranjan</surname></persname></person></author>
<author aff="affa"><person orcid="0000-0002-1547-6365" resid="G-8572-2012"><persname><fname>Maurice</fname><surname>van Gastel</surname></persname></person></author>
<author aff="affa"><person><persname><fname>Robert</fname><surname>Schlögl</surname></persname></person></author>
<aff id="affa"><org><orgname><nameelt>Department of Heterogeneous Catalysis</nameelt><nameelt>Max Planck Institute for Chemical Energy Conversion</nameelt><nameelt>Stiftstrasse 34-36</nameelt></orgname></org><address><city>Muelheim and Ruhr</city><postcode>45470</postcode><country>Germany</country></address><email>chinmoy.ranjan@cec.mpg.de</email></aff>
</authgrp>
<art-toc-entry>
<ictext>The structure of anodic iridium oxide (IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>) under water oxidation was explored using <it>in situ</it> Raman spectroscopy and theoretical calculations.</ictext>
<icgraphic id="ga" xsrc="c7cc05669a-ga.tif"/></art-toc-entry>
<abstract><p>The structure of anodic iridium oxide (IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>) under water oxidation was explored using <it>in situ</it> Raman spectroscopy and theoretical calculations. Isotopic substitution experiments and theoretical calculations confirmed formation of an IrO species during oxygen evolution reaction.</p></abstract>
</art-front>
<art-body>
<section>
<p>The oxygen electrode remains a central challenge in implementing a hydrogen-based economy.<citref idrefs="cit1 cit2">1,2</citref> IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> remains one of the most important catalysts for water oxidation reaction.<citref idrefs="cit3">3</citref> Dimensionally stable anodes (DSA) are composed of primarily IrO<inf>2</inf>.<citref idrefs="cit4 cit5 cit6 cit7 cit8">4–8</citref> These materials require being treated through activation protocols before they can be implemented. IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> materials were shown to be very active by Mallouk <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit9">9</citref> In the alkaline media, Mallouk <it>et al.</it> proposed that these materials are unstable and form molecular species that show oxygen activity.<citref idrefs="cit10">10</citref> In fact, the activity shown by these materials in alkaline electrolytes was much higher than in acidic or neutral electrolytes. We have recently characterized the active IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> material through <it>ex situ</it> Raman spectroscopy on anodic IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> grown on an iridium foil.<citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> Attempts to understand the mechanism of OER on IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> has encouraged operando studies using XPS and XAS.<citref idrefs="cit12 cit13">12,13</citref> These investigations focused on an Ir-centered approach to understanding the nature of the active catalyst. XPS studies observed an additional Ir 4f peak at higher binding energy (+0.7 eV) during OER and suggested an Ir<sup>5+</sup> species forming during the catalytic event.<citref idrefs="cit12">12</citref> Minguzzi <it>et al.</it> suggested the formation of both Ir<sup>3+</sup> and Ir<sup>5+</sup> during OER. But both these studies do not compare the shifts to standard Ir-containing compounds. High oxidation states (+5 or greater) are only known for fluorine-containing molecules amongst the stable Ir compounds or in IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> molecular species isolated within a noble gas matrix. Reier <it>et al.</it> and Pfeiffer <it>et al.</it> observed an additional feature at 529 eV in the O-Kedge NEXAFS spectra of highly OER active Ir–NiO<inf><it>x</it></inf> and amorphous IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> respectively. Using DFT calculations, they have suggested this to be an electrophilic oxygen species present in these materials.<citref idrefs="cit14 cit15 cit16">14–16</citref> By the nature of their inquiry, these studies cannot clarify the exact chemical nature of the IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> active site which is possible through vibrational spectroscopy. Mo <it>et al.</it> carried out <it>in situ</it> Raman spectroscopy on IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>/Au system but essentially used XAS data for interpretation of results.<citref idrefs="cit17">17</citref> Frei and coworkers have investigated IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> clusters as OER catalysts using rapid scan FTIR under visible light.<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> They reported detection of a transient Ir–OOH species with O–O vibration being detected at 830 cm<sup>−1</sup>. This work goes beyond work reported by Pavlovic <it>et al.</it> and uses <it>in situ</it> Raman spectroscopy to understand the behavior of these materials under conditions of OER.<citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> Specifically we focus on active site that forms <it>in situ</it>. We suggest a IrO species, with five coordinated square pyramidal Ir as the active site for water oxidation and suggest a mechanistic pathway for product formation and replenishment of the active site.</p>
<p>Cyclic voltammogram of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> materials in different electrolytes is well known (Fig. S1, ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>). All the potentials reported in this paper are referenced to the reversible hydrogen electrode (RHE). The material was electroprecipitated at 1.5 V onto a Au substrate as shown by Mallouk <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit9">9</citref> In our previous publication we have shown that the anodic Iridium oxide is essentially a hydrous material with OH and H<inf>2</inf>O groups playing important role in its overall structure.<citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> Experiments of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>/Au were conducted in an <it>in situ</it> Raman cell, using Biologic VSP-300 potentiostat. Raman spectra were collected with Ocean Optics QE65 pro spectrometer using 785 nm Laser source. The Laser intensity was maintained at 500 mW per 0.1 mm<sup>2</sup> at the sample (collection time of 10 s). The potential was scanned from 0.4–1.8 V, at steps of 0.1 V.</p>
<p>Results of the <it>in situ</it> Raman experiment are shown in <figref idrefs="fig1">Fig. 1</figref>. More details of the experiments are provided in the ESI.<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref> Peaks at 225 and 324 cm<sup>−1</sup> originate from the Au surface. The peaks from 450–780 cm<sup>−1</sup> originate from iridium oxygen vibrations, where peak assignments have been used from Pavlovic <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> Electrochemically, four regions (R) in the IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> CV can be clearly identified. R1(<it>E</it> &lt; 0.4 V), R2 (0.4 &lt; <it>E</it> &lt; 0.7 V), R3 (0.7 &lt; <it>E</it> &lt; 1.2 V) and R4 (<it>E</it> &lt; 1.4 V). Whereas R1 corresponds to a colorless compound rich in Ir<sup>3+</sup>, R2 represents the region of first oxidation wave from Ir<sup>3+</sup>↔ Ir<sup>4+</sup>. At the beginning of the experiment at OCP, there is a certain peak structure (465, 527, 600, 702 cm<sup>−1</sup>), which can be attributed to the Ir–O–Ir stretch vibrations of μ-oxo type from the basal plane of edge sharing IrO<inf>6</inf> octahedra.<citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> As soon as the potential of 0.4 V is applied, a sharp peak at 520 cm<sup>−1</sup> is formed. This is the most dominant peak <it>δ</it> in region R1. Region R1 has no ε peak which appears in R2. The ε peak loses intensity in R3. R4 shows significant drift of peaks γ → ε towards higher frequencies. At potentials 1.3 V and higher, AuO<inf><it>x</it></inf> is formed (Fig. S4, ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>). Thus peaks in R4 have substantial AuO<inf><it>x</it></inf> contribution to them. The final peaks observed at OCP in the treated materials are composed of both IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> and AuO<inf><it>x</it></inf> peaks. The peak η at 771 cm<sup>−1</sup> is seen in R4. This peak disappears as soon as the applied potential is switched off. This peak does not exist in experiments done on a bare Au surface and thus must be assigned to IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> material under conditions of water oxidation. Isotopic substitution using D<inf>2</inf>O and H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> as synthesis and reaction media were also carried out. Results have been tabulated in <tableref idrefs="tab1">Table 1</tableref>. <figref idrefs="fig2">Fig. 2</figref> shows effects of isotopic substitution on η. In the experiment that has 50 : 50 (H<inf>2</inf>O : H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref>), only two peaks of nearly equal intensity were visible. Thus this peak could be assigned to IrO vibration (as opposed to any other species that contained O–O, or OH vibration). If O movement is the primary oscillator in this vibration, then one can expect a shift of <ugraphic display="inline" id="ugt1" xsrc="c7cc05669a-t1.tif"/> upon O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> substitution. Deuterium substitution resulted in almost no shift of the peak (Δ<it>f</it> ∼ 5 cm<sup>−1</sup>). For Ir–O–OH containing groups, the shift reported by Frei <it>et al.</it> due to deuteration was 30 cm<sup>−1</sup>.<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> Small shifts due to deuteration are possible through altered hydrogen bonding contributions from the solvent. Vibrations where the motion of the hydrogen atom explicitly contribute to the vibrational mode show significant alteration of frequency upon deuteration due to the large mass change <ugraphic display="inline" id="ugt2" xsrc="c7cc05669a-t2.tif"/>. Fig. S5 (ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>) shows the results from various experiments with combinations of H<inf>2</inf>O, D<inf>2</inf>O, and H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> containing electrolytes. <figref idrefs="fig2">Fig. 2</figref>, shows η peak at OER potentials in variously labeled electrolytes. Fig. S5(d) (ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>) shows the results of experiments when material was synthesized in H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> and tested in H<inf>2</inf>O.<citref idrefs="cit16">16</citref> Peaks γ to ε begin to split into two sets of peaks in the beginning of R3 indicating that material exchanges oxygens with the electrolyte even at potentials as low as 0.7 V. Even the position of η peak only shows the contribution from O<sup>16</sup> isotope.</p>
<figure id="fig1" xsrc="c7cc05669a-f1.tif"><title>(a) <it>In situ</it> Raman spectroscopy of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>/Au system in 0.1 M NaOH. The peaks labeled by greek letters originate from Ir–O stretch vibrations. Rest of the peaks can be assigned to Au substrate (ESI,<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref> Section 2). η peak is only visible during the process of OER and disappears with removal of applied potential. Peak assignments (in greek letters) have been borrowed from Pavlovic <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref> (b) CV of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>/Au in 0.1 M NaOH (c) Average currents from <it>in situ</it> experiments in various electrochemical media.</title></figure>
<table-entry id="tab1"><title>Peaks obtained in the Raman spectra of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>/Au labeled at 0.8 V. The peaks tend to move with applied potential and thus their exact location can be described only at a certain potential. The Ir–O stretching assignments have been borrowed from Pavolovic <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit11">11</citref></title>
<table>
<tgroup cols="6">
<colspec colname="1" colnum="1"/>
<colspec colname="2" colnum="2"/>
<colspec colname="3" colnum="3"/>
<colspec colname="4" colnum="4"/>
<colspec colname="5" colnum="5"/>
<colspec colname="6" colnum="6"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Peak labels</entry>
<entry>H<inf>2</inf>O</entry>
<entry>D<inf>2</inf>O</entry>
<entry>H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref></entry>
<entry>1 : 1 (H<inf>2</inf>O : H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref>)</entry>
<entry>H<inf>2</inf>O<citref idrefs="cit18">18</citref> tested in H<inf>2</inf>O</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tfoot>
<row>
<entry nameend="6" namest="1"><footnote id="tab1fna">Collected at 1.7 V.</footnote></entry>
</row>
</tfoot>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>γ</entry>
<entry>476</entry>
<entry>475</entry>
<entry>423</entry>
<entry>454, 482</entry>
<entry>430, 458, 480</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>δ</entry>
<entry>527</entry>
<entry>554</entry>
<entry>476</entry>
<entry>541, 482</entry>
<entry>554</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>ε</entry>
<entry>595</entry>
<entry>602</entry>
<entry>554</entry>
<entry>605, 552</entry>
<entry>608</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>η<fnoteref idrefs="tab1fna"></fnoteref></entry>
<entry>771</entry>
<entry>767</entry>
<entry>712</entry>
<entry>722, 771</entry>
<entry>—</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</table-entry>
<figure id="fig2" xsrc="c7cc05669a-f2.tif"><title>Raman spectra of the η peak in various isotopically labeled electrolytes. The peaks are background corrected and normalized (details in Experimental section).</title></figure>
<p>Theoretical calculations using density functional theory were carried out to better understand the IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> system (Fig. S6–S8, ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>). Specifically, calculations were performed to understand the identity of the IrO species. A trimeric IrO<inf>6</inf> unit was used to construct a model system for calculation. It was found that an Ir–O unit on the central Ir atom resulted in the formation of a square pyramidal central Ir atom. [Ir<sup>4+</sup>–Ir<sup>4+</sup>–Ir<sup>4+</sup>] trimeric IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> cluster was used for computation (<figref idrefs="fig3">Fig. 3</figref>). The Ir–O vibration was computed to be at 829 cm<sup>−1</sup>. Furthermore it was found that the vibrations could be significantly modulated through hydrogen bonding near the “Ir–O” <it>e.g.</it> the Ir–O vibration was reduced to 766 cm<sup>−1</sup> from 829 cm<sup>−1</sup> by placing a H<inf>2</inf>O molecule near the Ir–O moiety. Besides, the relative intensity of this vibration was found to be very strong compared to the other vibrations within this molecule. We believe at the optimum potential some of the [IrO<inf>6</inf>]<inf><it>n</it></inf> species turn into the OER active IrO species that removes any further oxidative strain from the material. Even though present in much less quantity, the extremely high Raman activity of the Ir–O stretch vibration makes it possible for the active species to be detected within a matrix of [IrO<inf>6</inf>]<inf><it>n</it></inf> containing material. The 771 cm<sup>−1</sup> peak can also be detected in acidic media but has a much smaller intensity (the OER activity of the material in acidic and neutral media is much less than alkaline media (Fig. S2, ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>)). This is likely because the material is highly condensed in the acidic and neutral media and not many exposed active sites containing IrO species form, which gets reflected in the overall activity of the material. Ir–OOH species (Fig. S7, ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>) were also computed. The frequency of vibration of O–O stretch was 715 cm<sup>−1</sup>, besides the O–O stretch Raman intensity was much smaller. In light of our experimental and computational investigations we assign the observed 771 cm<sup>−1</sup> vibration to IrO stretch of a square pyramidal Ir site. The frontier orbitals of IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> were calculated and have been visualized in <figref idrefs="fig3">Fig. 3</figref>. The SOMO (<figref idrefs="fig3">Fig. 3(b)</figref>) shows that Ir–O unit is the most reactive part of the molecule with a major part of the molecular orbital localised in this region. The frontier orbitals are anti-bonding in nature between Ir-d and O-p with significant localization on O atom making it a suitable target for reaction. We believe this oxygen may be responsible for making the important O–O bond during the formation of molecular O<inf>2</inf> from water (<figref idrefs="fig4">Fig. 4</figref>). M–O species responsible for oxidizing water are common in literature.<citref idrefs="cit19">19</citref> In case of Mn-containing Photosystem II catalyst, the O–O bond formation either happens through a nucleophilic attack at the Mn–O center (Mn<sup>5+</sup>–O, Mn<sup>4+</sup>–O or Mn<sup>4+</sup>–oxyl) species or by an oxyl–oxyl radical coupling mechanism.<citref idrefs="cit20 cit21 cit22">20–22</citref> But the exact nature of the species is debatable. It has been suggested in the literature that an electrophilic oxygen at the active site is essential to make reactions like O–O bond formation and C–H bond activation, possible.<citref idrefs="cit16 cit23 cit24">16,23,24</citref> Wang <it>et al.</it> and Concepcion and coworkers suggested an O–O bond formation using nucleophilic attack on RuO site.<citref idrefs="cit25 cit26">25,26</citref> Using DFT based theory, Mai <it>et al.</it> suggested that C–H activation essentially consists of two parts, an Fe<sup>4+</sup>O species which was a precursor to Fe<sup>3+</sup>–O˙<sup>−</sup> oxyl species that carried out the hydrogen atom transfer.<citref idrefs="cit23">23</citref> Similarly, using DFT calculations Yang <it>et al.</it> have argued that Ru<sup>5+</sup>O can act as a precursor to Ru<sup>4+</sup>–O˙<sup>−</sup> oxyl species which carries out water O–O bond formation. For the IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> cluster shown in <figref idrefs="fig3">Fig. 3</figref>, the total Löwdin charge at the oxygen atom amounts to only −0.12 (as compared to −0.35 for the bridging oxo-s) and the Löwdin spin population at the central Ir and oxo amounts to 47% and 29%, respectively. Semantically, although this charge distribution would be compatible with a metal-oxyl (O˙<sup>−</sup>) species, the spin distribution rather indicates a much lower spin population at the oxygen (29%) than expected for a radical species (∼100%). This is the result of a somewhat covalent Ir–O π-interaction that involves the spin carrying d<inf><it>xz</it></inf> orbital (t<inf>2g</inf> in octahedral symmetry) at Ir (ESI<fnoteref idrefs="fn1"></fnoteref>). We believe what we see in our experiment, is the structure that is precursor to the reactive oxyl species as proposed by Mai and Yang <it>et al.</it><citref idrefs="cit23 cit24">23,24</citref> The observation of a reactive oxyl radical species under experimental conditions remains difficult, specifically at room temperature. Herlihy <it>et al.</it> observed an oxyl species on TiO<inf><it>x</it></inf> system using <it>in situ</it> ultrafast infrared spectroscopy.<citref idrefs="cit27">27</citref> Based on our data, we claim an Ir–O species that can in principle act as a precursor to a highly electrophilic oxyl species that reacts with water (or dissociated water) to form an O–O bond.</p>
<figure id="fig3" xsrc="c7cc05669a-f3.tif"><title>Theoretical calculations were carried out on IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> species containing with “Ir–O” moiety. The calculations resulted in an Ir–O species that was essentially square pyramidal at the Ir center. (Top) Ir<sup>4+</sup> containing species with the central atom having the Ir–O bond. The oxygen atom has been labeled with a O* (Top). (bottom) SOMO of the species.</title></figure>
<figure id="fig4" xsrc="c7cc05669a-f4.tif"><title>Proposed active species responsible for water oxidation in IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf> materials (alkaline media). Suggested mechanism of oxidation of water and regeneration of the active site is shown. The oxo species is likely to go through an oxyl type species before the O–O bond is formed.</title></figure>
<p>The scaffold enabling the OER is derived from a highly hydrous [IrO<inf>6</inf>]<inf><it>n</it></inf> species (of the type IrO<inf><it>x</it></inf>(OH)<inf><it>y</it></inf>(H<inf>2</inf>O)<inf><it>z</it></inf>), where each Ir atom is octahedrally coordinated by oxygens. Whereas the colour and vibrational spectroscopy of most of this material can be traced using <it>ex situ</it> spectroscopy, the formation of an active a square pyramidal “Ir–O” species is detectable only through <it>in situ</it> spectroscopy under applied potential. We propose that this Ir–O species is the active site within the molecule which is open to attack from H<inf>2</inf>O molecules leading to formation of O<inf>2</inf> through formation of an O–O bond as shown in <figref idrefs="fig4">Fig. 4</figref>. The OER chemistry is likely to proceed primarily in the ligand sphere.</p>
<p>The authors thank BMWi for supporting this work through grant 03ESP106D (EKOLYSER). Open Access funding provided by the Max Planck Society.</p>
</section>
<section><title>Conflicts of interest</title>
<p>There are no conflicts to declare.</p>
</section>
</art-body>
<art-back>
<biblist><citgroup id="cit1"><journalcit><citauth><fname>J. A.</fname><surname>Turner</surname></citauth><title>Science</title><year>2004</year><volumeno>305</volumeno><pages><fpage>972</fpage><lpage>974</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit2"><journalcit><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Schlögl</surname></citauth><title>ChemSusChem</title><year>2010</year><volumeno>3</volumeno><issueno>2</issueno><pages><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit3"><journalcit><citauth><fname>C. C. L.</fname><surname>McCrory</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S. H.</fname><surname>Jung</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J. C.</fname><surname>Peters</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. F.</fname><surname>Jaramillo</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2013</year><volumeno>135</volumeno><issueno>45</issueno><pages><fpage>16977</fpage><lpage>16987</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit4"><journalcit><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Hrussanova</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>E.</fname><surname>Guerrini</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Trasatti</surname></citauth><title>J. Electroanal. Chem.</title><year>2004</year><volumeno>564</volumeno><pages><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>157</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit5"><journalcit><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Damjanovic</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. K. Y.</fname><surname>Wong</surname></citauth><title>J. Electrochem. Soc.</title><year>1967</year><volumeno>114</volumeno><pages><fpage>592</fpage><lpage>593</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit6"><journalcit><citauth><fname>E.</fname><surname>Guerrini</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>H.</fname><surname>Chen</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Trasatti</surname></citauth><title>J. Solid. State. Electrochem.</title><year>2007</year><volumeno>11</volumeno><pages><fpage>939</fpage><lpage>945</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit7"><journalcit><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Trasatti</surname></citauth><title>Electrochim. Acta</title><year>1991</year><volumeno>36</volumeno><pages><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit8"><citation type="book"><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Trasatti</surname></citauth>, <title>Electrodes of Conductive Metallic Oxides, Part A and Part B</title>, <citpub><it>Elsevier</it></citpub>, <pubplace><it>Amsterdam</it></pubplace>, <year>1980–1981</year></citation></citgroup><citgroup id="cit9"><journalcit><citauth><fname>Y.</fname><surname>Zhao</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>N. M.</fname><surname>Vargas-Barbosa</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>E. A.</fname><surname>Hernandez-Pagan</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. E.</fname><surname>Mallouk</surname></citauth><title>Small</title><year>2011</year><volumeno>7</volumeno><issueno>14</issueno><pages><fpage>2087</fpage><lpage>2093</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit10"><journalcit><citauth><fname>Y.</fname><surname>Zhao</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>N. M.</fname><surname>Vargas-Barbosa</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. E.</fname><surname>Strayer</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>N. S.</fname><surname>McCool</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Maria-Erini Pandelia</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. P.</fname><surname>Saunders</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J. R.</fname><surname>Swierk</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J. F.</fname><surname>Callejas</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>L.</fname><surname>Jensen</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. E.</fname><surname>Mallouk</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2015</year><volumeno>137</volumeno><issueno>27</issueno><pages><fpage>8749</fpage><lpage>8757</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit11"><journalcit><citauth><fname>Z.</fname><surname>Pavlovic</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>C.</fname><surname>Ranjan</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>Q.</fname><surname>Gao</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>van Gastel</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Schloegl</surname></citauth><title>ACS Catalysis</title><year>2016</year><volumeno>6</volumeno><issueno>12</issueno><pages><fpage>8098</fpage><lpage>8105</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit12"><journalcit><citauth><fname>H. G.</fname><surname>Sanchez Casalongue</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>Ling Ng</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Kaya</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Friebel</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>H.</fname><surname>Ogasawara</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Nilsson</surname></citauth><title>Angew. Chem., Int. Ed.</title><year>2014</year><volumeno>53</volumeno><pages><fpage>7169</fpage><lpage>7172</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit13"><journalcit><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Minguzzi</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>O.</fname><surname>Lugaresi</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>E.</fname><surname>Achilli</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>C.</fname><surname>Locatelli</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Vertova</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>P.</fname><surname>Ghigna</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Rondinini</surname></citauth><title>Chem. Sci.</title><year>2014</year><volumeno>5</volumeno><pages><fpage>3591</fpage><lpage>3597</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit14"><journalcit><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Reier</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>Z.</fname><surname>Pawolek</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Cherevko</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>Bruns</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Jones</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Teschner</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Selve</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Bergmann</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>H. N.</fname><surname>Nong</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Schlögl</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>K. J. J.</fname><surname>Mayrhofer</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>P.</fname><surname>Strasser</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2015</year><volumeno>137</volumeno><issueno>40</issueno><pages><fpage>13031</fpage><lpage>13040</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit15"><journalcit><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Reier</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>H. N.</fname><surname>Nong</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Teschner</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Schlögl</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>P.</fname><surname>Strasser</surname></citauth><title>Adv. Energy Mater.</title><year>2016</year><pages><fpage>1601275</fpage></pages><link type="doi">10.1002/aenm.201601275</link></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit16"><journalcit><citauth><fname>V.</fname><surname>Pfeifer</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. E.</fname><surname>Jones</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J. J.</fname><surname>Velasco Vélez</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>C.</fname><surname>Massué</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. T.</fname><surname>Greiner</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Arrigo</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Teschner</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>F.</fname><surname>Girgsdies</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>Scherzer</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J.</fname><surname>Allan</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>Hashagen</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>G.</fname><surname>Weinberg</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>S.</fname><surname>Piccinin</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M.</fname><surname>Hävecker</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>A.</fname><surname>Knop-Gericke</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>R.</fname><surname>Schlögl</surname></citauth><title>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys.</title><year>2016</year><volumeno>18</volumeno><pages><fpage>2292</fpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit17"><journalcit><citauth><fname>Y.</fname><surname>Mo</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>I. C.</fname><surname>Stefan</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>W. B.</fname><surname>Cai</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J.</fname><surname>Dong</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>P.</fname><surname>Carey</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D. A.</fname><surname>Scherson</surname></citauth><title>J. Phys. Chem. B</title><year>2002</year><volumeno>106</volumeno><pages><fpage>3681</fpage><lpage>3686</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit18"><journalcit><citauth><fname>N.</fname><surname>Sivasankar</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>W. W.</fname><surname>Weare</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>H.</fname><surname>Frei</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2011</year><volumeno>133</volumeno><pages><fpage>12976</fpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit19"><journalcit><citauth><surname>Hohenberger</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Johannes</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Ray</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Kallol</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Meyer</surname></citauth><citauth><surname>Karsten</surname></citauth><title>Nat. Commun.</title><year>2012</year><volumeno>3</volumeno><pages><fpage>720</fpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit20"><journalcit><citauth><fname>N.</fname><surname>Cox</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D. A.</fname><surname>Pantazis</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>F.</fname><surname>Neese</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>W.</fname><surname>Lubitz</surname></citauth><title>Acc. Chem. Res.</title><year>2013</year><volumeno>46</volumeno><pages><fpage>1588</fpage><lpage>1596</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit21"><journalcit><citauth><fname>L.</fname><surname>Rapatskiy</surname></citauth><arttitle><it>et al.</it></arttitle><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2012</year><volumeno>134</volumeno><pages><fpage>16619</fpage><lpage>16634</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit22"><journalcit><citauth><fname>P. E. M.</fname><surname>Siegbahn</surname></citauth><title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title><year>2013</year><volumeno>1827</volumeno><pages><fpage>1003</fpage><lpage>1019</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit23"><journalcit><citauth><fname>B. K.</fname><surname>Mai</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>Y.</fname><surname>Kim</surname></citauth><title>Inorg. Chem.</title><year>2016</year><volumeno>55</volumeno><issueno>8</issueno><pages><fpage>3844</fpage><lpage>3852</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit24"><journalcit><citauth><fname>X.</fname><surname>Yang</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. H.</fname><surname>Baik</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2006</year><volumeno>128</volumeno><issueno>23</issueno><pages><fpage>7476</fpage><lpage>7485</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit25"><journalcit><citauth><fname>L. P.</fname><surname>Wang</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>Q.</fname><surname>Wu</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Van Voorhis</surname></citauth><title>Inorg. Chem.</title><year>2010</year><volumeno>49</volumeno><pages><fpage>4543</fpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit26"><journalcit><citauth><fname>J. J.</fname><surname>Concepcion</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. K.</fname><surname>Tsai</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>J. T.</fname><surname>Muckerman</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T. J.</fname><surname>Meyer</surname></citauth><title>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</title><year>2010</year><volumeno>132</volumeno><pages><fpage>1545</fpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup><citgroup id="cit27"><journalcit><citauth><fname>D. M.</fname><surname>Herlihy</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>M. M.</fname><surname>Waegele</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>X.</fname><surname>Chen</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>C. D.</fname><surname>Pemmaraju</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>D.</fname><surname>Prendergast</surname></citauth><citauth><fname>T.</fname><surname>Cuk</surname></citauth><title>Nat. Chem.</title><year>2016</year><volumeno>8</volumeno><pages><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>555</lpage></pages></journalcit></citgroup></biblist>
<compoundgrp></compoundgrp>
<annotationgrp></annotationgrp>
<datagrp></datagrp>
<resourcegrp></resourcegrp>
</art-back>
</article>
<?Pub Caret -2?>
<?Pub *0000036183 0?>
